and the harshness and all that and then
we finished the the ancient scriptural
proes that Rick is emptiness and now
we're going to go to the this would be
the standard presentation in a in a
monastery in a Tibetan Monastery okay
for Buddha nature first we get the
definition the teni of Buddha nature
which is very beautiful
[Applause]
is
say sesu
[Music]
I mean it would go like that but be like
10 times faster than that
okay all right like the first three
years in the moner was
like okay uh anything that can turn into
a Buddha is the definition of
R anything that can turn in G to Su a
Buddha s is the definition of Buddha
nature anything that could turn into a
Buddha is the definition of Buddha
nature
there's lots of debates like uh you
saying my finger Buddha nature
yeah okay is that emptiness no
okay like can your body turn into a
Buddha yes I think you could say yes
right uh is it emptiness no no so we're
going to have to tweak this a bit okay
but anyway basic definition anything
that can turn into a Buddha Okay so how
else is Buddha
nature could be well what I'm trying to
say is that you start to feel a
distinction between being Buddha nature
and having Buddha nature you are Buddha
nature you are Buddha nature why son a
good to because you can turn into a
Buddha okay can your emptiness turn into
a
Buddha
yeah right I mean when you change it
changes right well if we wouldn't say
change turn but become how
become doesn't change different basis
for the same emptiness you see emptiness
of our s is our calm is our uh that's
that's what I've been saying all along
that's what those three scriptures said
but now we got a different definition
anything that can turn into a Buddha is
Buddha nature so I just I want you to
feel there's going to be debate arising
and you'll get a lot of it in your
reading do I have Buddha nature or am I
Buddha nature the answer is both
okay you are bu you are Rick and you
have
Rick
okay you turns into Buddha and every
part of you turns into Buddha eventually
okay I used to say and don't forget the
distinction there's only one part of you
that doesn't change when you become a
Buddha your EMP which is your emptiness
okay so get that straight you know do
you become a Buddha yes does there a
part of you somehow transformed into a
Buddha yes um is there any part of you
which is will still be the same when
you're a Buddha yes but only my
emptiness okay got it um so that's the
definition of
Rick I'm going to give you the three
kinds of
Rick and then I'm going to stop with the
Tibetan so he can cruise on a little bit
okay um
de
[Music]
say there'll be three kinds of brutal
nature okay this is the first and the
most important okay this is the biggie
okay Rin means nature innate inbuilt
built in okay the Buddha nature that's
built in N means stays RI means Buddha
nature Buddha nature that stays by
Nature inside of you all the time you've
always had it you always will well
that's a tricky thing up till buddhahood
you'll have it okay big debates about
that okay but Ric this is the innate
Buddha nature okay
emptiness okay emptiness your
emptiness but if we were talking about
Buddha nature and The Emptiness being
the Buddha nature and that being the
foundation of certain accomplishments
would you want to make it a more
specific kind of
emptiness emptiness of s of your
thoughts yeah emptiness of your thoughts
but specifically The Emptiness of those
six realizations okay so if your
homework were to say give an example of
R you might say The Emptiness of the
Mind of a bodis SATA who's engaged in
the path of seeing who's in the direct
perception of shin The Emptiness of
their mind is a very important Rick
right The Emptiness in the mind of the
Mind of a person bodh SATA right could
be could have been lower track but we
want big time bodis SATA who's
perceiving emptiness directly The
Emptiness of their thoughts at that
moment is is a very good example of okay
it's an
innate nature of their mind it's the
it's the emptiness of their own mind
it's what makes it possible for them to
be having that thought
okay sorry well I don't want to call it
thought but perception let's call it
perception maybe more more accurate
let's call it the emptiness of the
perception or the wisdom sometimes they
call the emptiness of the wisdom of a
bodis SAA who's perceiving emptiness for
the first time directly okay um that's
now I just wanted to give you the
Sanskrit prti
say gotra we had gotra already it was a
TR for go which means
what yeah Cen which came to mean family
okay protection for C Tara for Gua okay
and then sta came into English as
station
stationary um all those words meaning to
stay that's the translation of n or
that's what n is a translation of and
prti means nature like it comes up a lot
in the yoga text you know prti meaning
natural pra meaning ahead like forward
comes from it proud comes from it prow
comes from it and then CTI like the root
for karma done we see it in the English
word serial present things like that
okay creation right
so is R okay that's now I'm going to
stop the Sanskrit I couldn't actually
find the Sanskrit for a lot of the
others it's pretty rare okay um but
since this is the main one I thought you
should have it I'm going to give you the
definition of this one into in
English ready this is direct quote
homework question
anything which is first of
all the realm of things and then I would
put in parenthesis emptiness that's just
a that's dhad right
CH okay anything which is first of all
the realm of things which means
emptiness and secondly can become the
Essence body of a Buddha the Essence
body of a Buddha so anything which is
emptiness
and can become the Essence body of a
Buddha is the definition of natural
Buddha nature natural inborn Buddha
nature innate Buddha nature that's the
big one that's the interesting one
that's the one you're focusing on when
you're seeing emptiness
directly The Emptiness of your own
thoughts at that moment okay that's the
big one that's the most important one it
turns into the essence Body Essence body
is what
but what is it how would you describe it
D it's part of the
dharmakaya yeah the emptiness of the
other bodies the other bodies yeah the
emptiness of the wisdom which is
nyaya the emptiness of the emanation
body The Emptiness of the Paradise Body
The Emptiness of those three other
bodies is the Essence body so it's
obviously the most important one because
it makes the other three possible okay
it gives place for the other three to
occur
okay and really when you see I'm this
directly the most amazing thing the one
thing which is the most extremely
powerful thing is this very concrete uh
feeling that the Buddha in the form of
emptiness is right here right here next
to you you know you have a
direct
uh like communion with the Buddha then
you know Buddha exists like you don't
see their form you see their Essence
body The Emptiness what you see is their
emptiness body so that's the big one
that's
like meeting the burning bush or
something you know it's like that kind
of thing if you ever see um
Charon Charlton hon throwing himself
down in front of the burning bush I mean
that's the exactly this this distinct
perception of a of the dharmakaya of the
Essence body of ab Buddha and so that's
the main event in the path of scene
that's what
makes it absolutely certain that you'll
become enlightened within a certain
amount of time seven lifetimes or less
one lifetime okay and then you will be
the protector of thousands of well
billions of Worlds of beings I mean you
know like it's one thing to work on a
project to help somebody you know like
like what we're doing today it's a
really good feeling you know we had a
group here today we're all working on
this project to help people but they
just imagine that you could serve
countless beings at the same time
without having to access sponsor you
know I mean wow you know that's really
something you know that's what we're
here for when you got to get People
Pumped up when you teach this when you
get to this point it's like imagine that
you were built to serve other people
that's all that makes us happy and then
you you can do it with countless beings
at the same time I mean it's like easy
you know so uh that's the important body
that's the real body that's the body
that makes it happen
Okay second uh oops oh that's kind of
nice can you see that okay no okay let's
TR
black Christy wouldn't like that one but
okay
say
G where's the
N it's this pral this is meaning future
tense take that off out say G you're in
trouble in the debate ground there's a
debate like that in the reading uh
actually not your reading you're going
to get but there's a debate in the in
the in the C textbook somebody makes a
mistake and says G which means developed
instead of G which means developable
developable I mean I'm just making up a
word okay in the in the homework it says
that which can be developed how's that
okay the
Rick which is which is devel which is
developing which can be developed okay
what it refers to I'll give you an
example let's see what examples on the
homework can be developed yeah the Rick
that can be
developed I don't have it let me think
about it what is that oh I got it you
could just say it's the direct
perception emptiness in the mind of a
bodh the wisdom itself what were we
talking about
before what was the natural
R the end of that wisdom now the wisdom
itself does that turn into a
Buddha
eventually sure sure I mean somewhere
down the line that state of mind is
going to turn into a Buddhist State of
Mind inevitably okay therefore it
qualifies as Rick as come as Buddha
nature it is Buddha
nature it'll turn into a Buddhist mind
sooner or later okay that's all that's
slightly different than what You' been
teaching yeah the big Rick is the
emptiness yeah okay but you can say that
the mind is also Buddha nature okay
because it will turn into a Buddha and
it's different from what I've been
saying all along okay I mean 99% of Rick
is covered by The Emptiness of of the B
buddhis off's perception of
emptiness but uh you can also say that
mind itself the perception itself is
going to it's it's going to turn into a
Buddhist mind sooner or later right
somewhere down the Road your mind if
it's not already will become a Buddhist
mind so you can call it rick because the
definition of Rick is what come anything
that can turn into a budha
okay so g means developable you know
which can be developed or which can
be what do you call that when you uh
grow crops
cultivated yeah which can be cultivated
into a buha okay is is one kind of rig
okay it's not the main
one okay but it is one kind of rig still
it's not like some kind of Buddha that's
already inside you right that's not that
would not be developable that would be
fully developed and this would be past
tense and okay but is your state of mind
tonight in a sense something that will
become a Buddha you can say that uh well
depends there's a debate about denzen
ignorance you know will that become a
Buddha
that's a debate okay third
one and then we'll stop with the Tibetan
and go on to the tanc thing which is
sexy
to
say de
sh Rick De sha means other kind other
than
those than those de shamba means other
kinds of Rick Ricks other kinds of
Buddha nature Buddha Natures which
aren't covered by natural Buddha nature
and developable Buddha nature okay and
he's hard pressed to give any examples
but he just does it to cover himself in
a debain and the one of the example he
that I would give is um let's say that
you reach the direct perception
emptiness something happens to your
opinion of the Buddhist path
what it's all doubt doubt is totally
gone forever forever I mean whatever
happens in your life up or down you'll
never doubt Buddhism again ever you
know so do you in a sense possess the
absence of
Doubt yes yeah in Nai Dharma system they
say there grows on you a a
belt a psychic belt which holds the
absence of
doubt I mean Aid Dharma even makes it
into a an actual like a Halo that grows
around you and holds in your absence of
doubt you'll yeah it's very weird but it
connects that lack of Doubt to you you
own that lack of Doubt forever that lack
of Doubt is glued to your body to your
being forever it's a linked chain to
your being
okay will you is that a Rick is that
lack of Doubt a
rick a lack of Doubt a rick you can say
so the fact that you've lost out forever
will that turn into a
Buddha it's it's
cultivable
well it's an absence it's a simple 100%
absence which can never want
change it's just an absence absence of
self-existence absence of a three-headed
purple 14ot elephant in this room and
absence of doubt in an audience's
mind are all equally 100% nothing you
know it's not like they're going to be
more empty or less empty or he's going
to have 100% lack of Doubt or 39% lack
of doubt it's 100% unchangeable un
irrevocable immutable lack of do so it's
not changing so we can't call it what
kind of
Rick it's not cultivate can't cultivate
it it's not going to happen anything to
it can we call it the first kind of rck
the innate one that you've always had
that was born in you that was under the
floor of your house all that time you
didn't know no because he got it later
so ki our textbook writer says we better
make a Third Kind here other kinds of
Rick okay and that's just a weird
example okay I mean that's something if
you want to confuse the people into son
you can bring that up I want I forgot to
give you the definition in English of
the
developable uh Rick and then we're done
with this part we can go to the tantric
stuff it's a little more fun and it's
short it's like five minutes or
something or
[Music]
so okay here's the definition of Buddha
nature that can be developed right
developable uh
anything which can
become one of the caused
bodies anything which can become one of
the caused
bodies at the level of a
Buddha see there's four bodies right I
mean you can say two three or four right
but if you do four how many are caused
and how many are not caused three are
caus three sorry three caused one not
caused this is the emptiness body the
Essence body okay is the wisdom of a
Buddha the omniscience of a Buddha the
omnicient body is that caused we hope so
okay how about the body they send down
to earth we hope so how about the body
they sit with in their Paradise it's
caused so so these are all caused by G
by developable Buddha nature this one is
sort of just the extension of the
natural Buddha nature you know the final
evolution of the we don't even want to
use a word that would imply change you
see it's the final stage of urinate
Buddha nature this one and these three
are all developed these are three
changing caused Parts caused bodies at
the level of a Buddha okay that's all so
could you have developable Buddha nature
at the level of a
Buddha no because it's the cause for
them you see okay that's
all okay we're on to the tantric thing
this is more
interesting if you uh wanted to uh if it
required wisdom to find out the tantric
presentation all this who what de would
you want to call
on manushi say okay manushi and if you
couldn't talk to manushi directly uh and
you lived in 1357 to
1419 uh who would you want to
call no
no no no if you lived 1357 to 1419 and
you couldn't speak to to MRI directly
who would you want to call do you
remember we had it
briefly Lama umap say it umap okay Lama
umap it means uh you know Mr middle
way this was jessen cop's great teacher
who was a I don't know if you remember
he was a u a yak herd he was a sheep H
herder he grew up out in the mountains
in diamond mountain somewhere heating
you know and he would sit there and he
got a blessing from MRI he got like
practices from MRI and he met MRI and he
made contact sadna dupt D he met he made
contact you know with manduri and then
his whole life he became a great
philosopher and he was hurting sheep his
whole life I mean people MAA is just a
sheeper then when Jess Kaa wanted to ask
questions about from MRI before he met
manjushri he this was the intermediary
Lama umap okay so we have books written
by L mapa and you know I'm just
searching sort of a uh a Content check
with the database and I hit this book
that has a perfect explanation of the
tantric process and then I look who
wrote it and it's lamu mapa so this is
from lamu mapa's it's called a
collection of text on MRI it's from a
book called a collection of works on MRI
and it's by Lama who didn't write a lot
it's very
interesting being a sheep herder
right and what I want to do is
um there's going to be a
negativity a mental Affliction some
rotten part of our mind okay that's
going to be the first
part then there's going to be a a
heap a scanda one of the five parts of
ourselves okay and then there's going to
be a Buddha wisdom
that's three third part yeah this is one
two three I'm going to give you the
Tibetan what the hell there's a
DOA sorry there's a
DOA and there's a pumo I'm sorry there's
a Nar
and there's a
yes t means negativity no I was going to
say what does taka
mean we we had it last class you were
talking about bodh saf number 140 seeing
all being is pure taka so taka means
totally pure suda in Sanskrit pure
totally pure it means get rid of this
negativity P purify yourself of that
negativity okay clean it out of your
system totally permanently that's called
Daka
then you'll get to the ne T NE means
transformation N means Place gear means
change neure means final transformation
if you could purify certain mental
afflictions the five parts of your being
would begin to
transform until they reach the ultimate
transformation that's called NE taruk
the ultimate
transformation physical body turns into
you know rainbow uh illary Bonny tantric
Bonny
okay but those two things also trigger a
kind of wisdom in the enlightened being
that you will become okay when you
purify certain mental afflictions this
is all
Tantra certain Transformations take
place the ultimate form of which is a
certain kind of wisdom within a Buddha
okay so I want to give you the the the
list how many items will there be on
this list
five they correspond to the five heaps
okay what is the ultimate transformation
of your body what is the ultimate
transformation of your feelings what is
the ultimate transformation of your
ability to discriminate what is the
ultimate transformation of everything
else about you and what is the ultimate
transformation of your Consciousness the
five heaps and which which mental
afflictions do you purify to trigger
them especially and when that all
happens what kind of the five beautiful
parts of a Buddha are you going to have
okay and it's only taught in Tantra
clearly okay it's very cool um there's a
little bit in the sarahj textbooks those
of you who got the angel teachings I
don't you may remember that it was in
there some of it was in there okay so
here we
go uh so we'll do it's going to be
negativity
Heap and and wisdom
right and we'll have five items um the
first negativity that you get rid of is
is
anger the purification is is of your
Consciousness don't think of this as a
big word and a complicated thing it's
just the fact that you're aware right
now Mike Tyson punches you hard enough
this one goes to a lower level that's
all the fact that you're alive the fact
that you can see anything the fact that
you're even thinking now that you're
aware of anything is like a miracle it's
totally unbelievable you know billions
and billions of beings for every person
here have this screwed up Consciousness
they can't perceive anything they're in
darkness they're cold they're suffering
they can't think a b c d nothing just
pain just stupidity we're in a very
incredible Realm that you have
Consciousness you know you can think
you're aware you know you see where you
are you know it's precious you lose it
when you die I mean it changes so badly
that when you go into the B it's like
you it might as well not be there okay
so we want to get the change before that
happen Okay so anger if you can purify
your anger in tantric terms it has some
deep connection to the Heap of
Consciousness and you get what we call
mirror wisdom
uh there's a boo boo in the homework
hang on
uh
oh sorry okay made a boo boo in the
homework Master whoever's watching
that
uh
pride and um there's not a good English
word for this it means you don't want to
give things to other people what do you
want to call that stingy stingy
I call you call it cheap cheapness is a
little too
economically but let's call it that or
possessiveness how about possessiveness
you don't want to share you want to you
don't want to
give the same thing uh not really but
they're just that he's going to go
through major negative thoughts that we
all have and then how you can if you
purify them it triggers certain changes
in your heaps this happens to be the
Heap of uh
feeling this is up
mhm okay so I fixed it
okay feeling and this is what we call
equal
wisdom I think you would I'm not sure I
would have said a kagu maybe but I'm not
sure yeah can you define pride uh Nagel
nine kinds right I mean thinking you're
better than someone who's much better
than you thinking you're better than
people are equal to you thinking you're
much more important than people are
lesser than you and then there's a the
whole but not Gil I'm
king um I thought I'd tell you a little
bit about these wisdoms they're pretty
complicated but
um obviously there are different facets
of the omniscience that you will have
when you become an enlightened being if
you're not one already okay mirror like
means you know when you look into a
mirror it's a very big emphasis on
subject and object you know like I'm out
here and the object is over there but
even in a mirror it's who babies don't
see it right babies think what some they
think it's somebody else but at a
certain point you realize that it's you
and the same thing happens with your
understanding of especially those of you
who took S Class there's a certain point
at which you really appreciate that the
guy who pisses you off is is your
projection so the idea of subject and
object it's not that they're exactly the
same thing but but you begin to
appreciate that you've created this
object who's getting you angry
and then you obviously that becomes
useful in the Buddhist path you instead
of fighting with them you take steps to
eliminate them instead of perpetuating
them you take steps to eliminate them
intelligently okay uh so mirrorlike
wisdom is that sort of understanding of
subjects and objects the real
understanding that the Buddha's perfect
grasp of the relationship between
subjects and objects is is emphasized by
that wisdom
equal refers especially to the Buddhist
omniscience being having totally uh
equinity towards all beings okay which
has developed through billions of years
of practicing
D exchanging self and other okay
billions and billions of years of that
practice then you might get to this
aspect of a Buddha's wisdom these are
called the five wisdoms by the way of a
Buddha
yes okay number
three I think is uh
oh here we could have said
ignorant
disliking
right
yeah what do you guess about the Heat
any
guesses discrimination yeah let's call
it
discrimination and this is called
analytical wisdom
this just means the ability of a
Buddhist mind that grew out of that
Buddha's ability to start figuring it
out like the ration The Logical of the
Perfection of wisdom what Perfection of
wisdom means okay I want to get rid of
this person who's bothering me in my
life you know like I'm tired of
suffering I want to get rid of the
people who irritate me now
logically it must not be the solution
just to get mad at them and fight with
them because it doesn't work so maybe
it's my karma and maybe I should you
know be nice to people and then I won't
have to meet these people anymore you
know that is the final development of
that is is analytic what we call the
anal litical wisdom side of a Buddha
sori okay like Buddha figured stuff out
perfectly you know and that's from
eliminating ignorant black yeah somehow
now you figured out I haven't worked on
it I haven't worked on you figur it out
you know why does the why does the Daka
the purification of
these have a deep connection to these
aspects of a Buddhist wisdom you figure
it out you help your students figure it
out in Tucson you know no you go home
and think about it I didn't do it
personally you know I've read it I've
seen it it comes in a lot of
um sadas like the sod Tara it states
these same correlations you know and
they're very beautiful
oh I got rid of my pride and
possessiveness my habit of feeling
things has transformed into equality
wisdom of a budha you know what I mean
and it's a prayer it's part of a chant
that you do to Tara for example so you
figure it out you know these are very
deep you don't see them much you I don't
think you can get any of them after
1400s I mean it's there's something
going on there I think you should work
on it let me know okay no really okay uh
number
four oh
cool
jealousy one of my
specialties actually I overcame jealousy
and three Retreat and replaced it with
angry you see
so
okay uh there wasn't anything to be
jealous of uh except the rabbits and
stuff
uh other we call it other factors right
you know
that I've heard it also called form I
hate that
one no it's not it's samsar but it
doesn't mean that meaning of Samar
that's a Mis transation that's just a
mistake it's just a
mistake what does it
mean first chapter the fourth Heap is
defined as all the other stuff about
you okay that makes things happen
literally that's what sansara means so
they've mistaken the sansara which means
in in The Wheel of Life the second link
D which does mean karmic formations so
they they it's the same word in Sanskrit
and Tibetan but it has totally different
meanings uh in different context they
just made a mistake it's a mistake
um the technical word samcar though
means stuff that makes other stuff
happen Okay and there's a wisdom called
the wisdom of being able to do things
you know I'll call it accomplishment
wisdom but you know what it means jadui
means get things done getting things
done okay I'll put accomplishment for
all those scholarly
people or accomplishing wisdom how's
that if you're sitting there in a Buddha
field and you're already in enlightened
and you're sitting in your enlightened
Buddha Paradise Angel beautiful light
body right which will happen if you
succeed in this course
uh what do you got to
do what do you got to accomplish what
what did they do everybody El yeah they
get other people enlightened how Stand
Out bodies Stand Out bodies near ma near
Mana uh send out Manaka tuku send out
tokul you know that's what's the real
meaning of tuul is send out those bodies
so this kind of wisdom is specifically
that um part of a Buddhist omniscience
which is sending out bodies
spontaneously without premeditation okay
um due to this you see you see how you
get the word factor which means to do
something cause something make something
happen this the connection between these
two is a little clear why jealousy
connects to
that you know why does the purification
of our jealousy suddenly contribute to
the Buddhist wisdom which allows them to
send out bodies is it that jealousy
somehow prevents us from getting what we
want done I don't know you come back to
me we'll have a discussion at the
beginning of next class okay I'm just
curious how you come up with I don't I
don't have any magic answers and this is
called from about 200,000 pages of
scripture so I mean this is I give you
the essence of hundreds of thousands of
pages of scripture I mean they don't
have more than this so we have to
struggle with done okay uh last
one what's one big mental Affliction
that we got left big
ignorance we only got one Heap
left form
body oh yeah
it's called dhad wisdom okay Dharma
realm wisdom we just said that CH Ying
is a synonym for
what y dad dadatu which meant what
emptiness emptiness itself the textbook
writer sah J Who presents this said look
this is emptiness itself it's not it's
called the fifth wisdom it's always
called the fifth wisdom of a Buddha but
it's really The Emptiness of the other
wisdoms you sound familiar like the
Essence body like the uh
Sakaya
okay so if you could get rid of your
ignorance then somehow your physical
body would somehow transform into the
emptiness of the other wisdom
you you deal with it okay I think it's
really cool it feels right right it
feels like something very deep going on
here you know they don't talk about this
when they talk about Buddha nature and
developing Buddha nature and final
transformation of Buddha nature but when
you get to
Tantra they start you start seeing this
so you work on it this is the ultimate
evolution of the idea of Buddha nature
somehow these the purification of these
negative emotions is causing a final
transformation of our normal old stinky
body and mind into these incredible
parts of a Buddha you know how does that
how how does it all work what are the
connections what are the correlations
you got to work on that okay I think
it'd be really cool somehow I think that
you should spend a lot of time on this
one in your classes in tuon you know
like uh somehow it feels very right to
talk about if you could get rid of your
jealousy you know you'd be able to send
out your bodies
you know I think it'd be really cool to
look into that okay explore it do that
part experimentally right I think that
might even be your homework I'm not sure
okay uh next Wednesday we get the
fight okay onck and then you're Masters
on then you know more about Buddha
nature than most than 99% of the monks
in all the monasteries tell you the
truth so um that'll be nice
okay here we go
[Music]
B ch
for nature
[Music]
cool